<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The preachers president, or, The master and scholler in a sermon preached at a synode holden by the Right Reuerend Father in God, Iohn, Lord Bishop of Chester, at Wigan in Lancashire, the 21 of Aprill, 1625 / by Iames Hyatt B. of D. and preachers of Gods Word at Liuer-poole.</title>
            <author>Hyatt, James, fl. 1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03930</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2753</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24585979</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24585979</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27804</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03930)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27804)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1854:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The preachers president, or, The master and scholler in a sermon preached at a synode holden by the Right Reuerend Father in God, Iohn, Lord Bishop of Chester, at Wigan in Lancashire, the 21 of Aprill, 1625 / by Iames Hyatt B. of D. and preachers of Gods Word at Liuer-poole.</title>
                  <author>Hyatt, James, fl. 1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A² B-C⁴ D².</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XXII, 16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27804:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27804:1"/>
            <p>THE PREACHERS PRESIDENT, OR THE <hi>MASTER</hi> AND SCHOLLER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a Sermon preached at a Synode, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by the Right Reuerend Father</hi> in <hi>GOD, IOHN,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>CHESTER,</hi> at <hi>Wigan in</hi> Lancaſhire, <hi>the 21. of Aprill. 1625.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>IAMES HYATT,</hi> B. of D. and Preacher of Gods Word at Liuer-Poole.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>William Stansby.</hi> 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:27804:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27804:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER <hi>IN</hi> GOD, <hi>John,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> my ſingular good Lord and Patron.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY GOOD LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N obedience to your Lordſhips pleaſure, I doe here humbly preſent you with that Sermon, which I lately preacht, by your Lordſhips ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, at <hi>Wigan:</hi> my little leaſure, and health at that time, and my leſſe skill for ſuch a buſineſſe, made me very vnwilling to vnder-take it, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcious to my ſelfe that I ſhould not ſufficiently diſcharge it: but your Lordſhips authoritic impoſing it vpon mee, brought me to a neceſsitie of performing it, as I could; and when I had done it, your Lordſhip was pleaſed (to my great incouragement) not onely to ſpeake well of it, but to require a re-view of it from mine hand and pen: And, indeed your fauour and goodneſſe to me and mine, hath beene ſuch, and taken ſo deepe impreſsion in mine heart, that I ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:27804:3"/>haue power to denie, whatſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to command, or expect from me, though otherwiſe, I could rather haue wiſht that it might haue ſlept with me in ſilence. For, it may be, thoſe defects will be ſpyed in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, which were not ſo eaſily obſerued in the hearing of it.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe that the <hi>matter</hi> is, much of it, gathered from others, onely the <hi>method</hi> is mine owne, and if it proue therefore leſſe acceptable to ſome, who by this meanes may chance to haue a ſight of it, yet I am confident, that this ſhall bring no loſſe to it, in your Lordſhips acceptation: as well knowing that the <hi>Spiders web</hi> is no whit the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, becauſe it is all wouen out of her owne bowells; nor the <hi>Bee's honey</hi> leſſe pleaſant and vſefull, becauſe it is gathered from ſeuerall flowers.</p>
            <p>Whatſoeuer it be, I now commit it to your Lordſhips Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, humbly deſiring (ſeeing it hath found grace in your eyes) that it may ſafely ſhelter it ſelfe vnder your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and continue with you, if for no other vſe, yet as a faithfull pledge of mine hearts thankfulneſſe, which hath for euer vowed it ſelfe to your Lordſhips ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ice.</p>
            <p>And now, crauing pardon for this boldneſſe, I humbly commend your good Lordſhip to the mercy of God in Chriſt Ieſus, beſeeching him, vpon the bended knees of mine heart, to bleſſe you with health, long life, and happy dayes vpon earth, to his glorie and his Churches good, and with eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall felicitie hereafter in his heauenly Kingdome.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humbly deuoted Chaplaine, IAMES HYATT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27804:3"/>
            <head>THE PREACHERS PRESIDENT, OR THE MASTER AND SCHOLLER.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATTH. 22.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And they ſent out vnto him their Diſciples with the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodians, ſaying, Maſter we know that thou art true, and teacheſt the way of God in truth, neither carest thou for any man, for thou regardeſt not the perſon of men.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He latter wordes of this Text may fitly bee called <hi>The Preachers preſident,</hi> for they contayne in them the exact deſcription of ſuch a man as is fit to teach Gods Will to the World, as will more fully appeare in the after handling of them, the occaſion of their deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie may be thus conceiued; The Phariſies had before aſſayed to reſiſt Chriſt openly, but when they ſee that that will doe no good, they withdraw themſelues from him; and thinke vpon a fraudulent courſe againſt him, which is by ſome meanes to intangle him in his talke; and becauſe they foreſee that their owne perſons are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:27804:4"/>no fit inſtruments for ſuch a purpoſe (hauing before diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered themſelues and their malice againſt his Perſon and Doctrine) therefore they <hi>ſend their Diſciples with the Herodians to him;</hi> two Sects, though differing much both in life and Religion, yet agreeing well enough to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to deſtroy Chriſt; which, that they may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doe, they are to fayne themſelues <hi>iuſt men.</hi> And to ſay to him;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.20.</note> 
               <hi>Maſter, we know that thou art true, and teacheſt the way of God in Truth, neither careſt thou for any men, for thou regardest not the perſon of men; Tell vs therefore, what thinkeſt thou, is it lawfull to giue tribute to Caeſar, or not?</hi> which ſpeech of theirs, diuideth it ſelfe into a <hi>ſalutation</hi> and a <hi>queſtion;</hi> I haue now choſen the firſt of them onely to ſpeake of. In handling it, I might obſerue the <hi>manner</hi> of their ſaluting Chriſt, and the <hi>matter</hi> of their ſalutation; for the <hi>manner,</hi> it is very diſſemblingly done of them, for they come with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to deſtroy Chriſt, and yet giue him good wordes; call him Maſter, and tell him, that they know him to be thus and thus qualified (as indeed it becommeth euery Maſter of Gods people to be) but vnder this maske of faire wordes, they ſeeke to ſhroud the wicked purpoſe of their hearts from his obſeruation; they pretend loue to his perſon, and reuerence to his profeſſion, that they may ſecretly draw him into the ſnare which they haue priuily laid for him; which indeed is the common pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of falſe-hearted flatterers; it is vſuall with them to hide the deadly hooke of their wicked purpoſes vnder the ſugered bait of faire wordes,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.3.</note> and to come like <hi>Ioab</hi> with <hi>art thou in health, my brother?</hi> or <hi>Iudas</hi>-like, with <hi>all haile Maſter</hi> in their mouthes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.49.</note> when there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but treaſon and villainie in their hearts. But I cannot ſtay vpon this point, my purpoſe is to inſiſt one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27804:4"/>vpon the <hi>matter</hi> of their ſalutation, which is the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribing of three particular qualities to Chriſt, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed were moſt eminently in himſelfe, and ought, in ſome competencie, to bee in euery Miniſter of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Chriſt Ieſus. The firſt is, that hee was <hi>true,</hi> the ſecond, <hi>a teacher of the truth</hi> to others, the third, <hi>no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecter of mens perſons,</hi> the firſt ſeemeth to haue reference to his <hi>perſon,</hi> the ſecond to his <hi>miniſterie,</hi> the third to both; as if they ſhould haue ſaid; wee know thee to bee one that doeſt rightly vnderſtand, and conſtantly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne and practiſe the truth in thine owne perſon, and alſo diligently &amp; faithfully to teach it others, not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it to receiue any detriment, either in thy life or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, through partialitie, or reſpect of mens perſons.</p>
            <p>So that in theſe words they acknowledge Chriſt to bee an vpright and blameleſſe liuer in his owne perſon, and a faithful and diligent teacher of the truth to others. Which two things indeed are neceſſarily required, if not to the <hi>being,</hi> yet to the perfecting of our miniſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all function,<note place="margin">Exod. 28.30.33.</note> they were repreſented by the <hi>Vrim and Thummim</hi> in <hi>Aarons</hi> breſt plate, &amp; the <hi>golden bells</hi> and <hi>Pomegranets</hi> about the skirts of his Garment; whereby God ſignified that he would haue light of doctrine ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with integritie of life; and the ſweet ſound of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing words, to bee accompanied with the ſauorie fruits of good workes, in all them that ſhould draw neere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him in the ſeruice of his Altar.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe Chriſt couples them together in the New Teſtament, <hi>whoſoeuer ſhall doe</hi> and <hi>teach the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the ſame ſhall bee called great in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heauen.</hi> And hee teſtifieth of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, that he was <hi>a burning and a ſhining lampe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.19.</note> 
               <hi>burning in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe</hi> by the holineſſe of his life, <hi>and ſhining to others</hi> by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27804:5"/>the puritie of his doctrine. And the Apoſtle exhorts the Elders of <hi>Epheſus</hi> that they ſhould take heede to themſelues and to the flocke ouer which the holy Ghoſt had made them ouerſeers:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28.</note> to the flock by feeding them with the foode of wholſome doctrine, and to themſelues by liuing in their owne perſons, according to that which they taught to others. So that theſe two being neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly required in euery faithfull Miniſter, and ioyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Holy Ghoſt, ought not by any meanes to be found ſeuered in any that take vpon them to be maſters of Gods people; but though they may not be ſeparated in a Miniſters practiſe, yet, for the better opening of my Text, and fitting of it to the preſent occaſion, I muſt ſpeake of them ſeuerally, as they are in order laid downe to vs in the words of my Text.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing then which they aſcribe to Chriſt, is, that he is <hi>true, Maſter wee know that thou art true.</hi> Which ſeemeth to me to inferre three things, firſt that he knew the truth, (that muſt needes bee implyed) ſecondly that he vſed to ſtand ſtifly to it, and to maintaine it againſt the oppoſers of it, for thats, <hi>eſſe veracem,</hi> to be one that not onely hath the truth in himſelfe, but holdes and vpholds it againſt others. Thirdly that he was faithfull and ſincere in all his proceedings, leading an innocent and blameleſſe life amongſt them. And that Chriſt was true in himſelfe in all theſe reſpects, is moſt euident to vs that know the truth, ſo that to ſpend time in the proofe of it, were but to hold a candle to the Sunne; but as they were eminently in Chriſt, ſo ought they to bee compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tently in euery Miniſter of Chriſt Ieſus. Firſt it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie that euery maſter ouer Gods people ſhould <hi>know</hi> the <hi>truth,</hi> for as Chriſt when hee firſt came to viſit in mercie, vpbraided <hi>Nicodemus</hi> with the want of this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27804:5"/>which he obſerued to be in him; <hi>art thou a maſter of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael and knoweſt not theſe things?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.10.</note> ſo much more when he ſhall come the ſecond time to viſit in Iudgment, he will queſtionleſſe bee highly offended with thoſe that haue taken vpon them to ſet themſelues down in the Maſters Chayre, when the ſchollers forme would better haue becom'd their ignorance. No wiſe man ſends a meſſage of importance by the mouth of a foole; &amp; ſhall we thinke that Almighty God ſends thoſe to bee his meſſengers in the Miniſterie of his Goſpell to the World, that runne like <hi>Ahimaaz,</hi> without their errand? no,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam</hi> 18.23.</note> God him ſelfe hath foretold vs, that though ſuch <hi>runne,</hi> yet <hi>hee hath not ſent them;</hi> for whom he ſends,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 14.14.</note> he firſt tels them their errand, and teacheth them that truth by his word and Spirit, which he ſends them to teach to others.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is neceſſarie too, that as euery Miniſter ſhould <hi>haue the truth</hi> in himſelfe, ſo hee ſhould <hi>hold</hi> and <hi>maintaine</hi> it againſt thoſe that oppoſe it; for ſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> chargeth. <hi>Titus,</hi> that <hi>hee ſhould ordaine none,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>but thoſe that ſhould hold faſt the faithfull word, being able by ſound doctrine both to exhort and to conuince gaine-ſayers.</hi> And he preſently addes this reaſon, <hi>for there are many vnruly and vains talkers, and deceiues whoſe mouthes must bee ſtopt;</hi> meaning by ſtrength of reaſon, and force of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument: and therefore ſtraight way after hee aduiſeth <hi>Titus</hi> himſelfe to vſe ſuch <hi>ſound ſpeech in his doctrine as cannot be condemned;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>that he which is on the contrarie part may be aſhamed</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>when he ſhall haue nothing to ſay againſt you.</hi> So that euery Miniſter is to bee furniſhed with a double knowledge; <hi>Dogmaticall,</hi> and <hi>Polemicall;</hi> that he may not onely be able to <hi>reach</hi> and <hi>exhort,</hi> but to <hi>conuince</hi> gaine-ſayers; being the ſhepheard of Gods ſheepe, he muſt haue a two-fold voyce; one to gouerne
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27804:6"/>and call in, and keep together his ſheepe, which muſt be gentle, &amp; familiar to them; and another to driue away Wolues, which muſt be fearefull and terrible to them; one to teach and ſtabliſh the truth, and another to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, or ſupplant and roote vp Hereſies and Errours, like <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> builders who held a Trowell in one hand,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neb.</hi> 4.17.</note> and a Sword in the other.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, euery Maſter is not only to haue &amp; to hold the truth,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16</note> but to liue according to it. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tels <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> that of all elſe, <hi>Biſhops and Ministers muſt bee blameleſſe, and men of good report, euen of thoſe that are without.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16</note> And therefore afterward, hee bids <hi>Timothy</hi> himſelfe that he ſhould <hi>take heed as well to himſelfe as to his doctrine.</hi> And <hi>Titus,</hi> that hee ſhould <hi>ſhew himſelfe in example of good workes to others. A Ministers life is,</hi> indeed, the very <hi>life of his Miniſtery,</hi> it is to little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, for vs to commend the <hi>ſtraite way</hi> to others, that leads <hi>to heauen,</hi> if our ſelues runne before them in the <hi>broad way</hi> that leadeth <hi>to Hell</hi> for,<note place="margin">Greg. Pag.</note> 
               <hi>Cum Paſtor per ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupta graditur, ad praecipitium grex ſequitur.</hi> When the Shepheard himſelfe goeth before in dangerous and ſteepe downe places, the flocke cannot but follow after head-long to their owne deſtruction. The life of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter is an exemplary teaching of his people; for the moſt do more marke our <hi>liues</hi> then our <hi>Learning:</hi> ſo that he which <hi>liueth ill,</hi> though he <hi>preach well,</hi> by his <hi>life,</hi> puts a <hi>lye</hi> vpon the truth which he preacheth, and puls down that with one hand which he ſeemeth to build with the other. There is no one thing which makes our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery (which is in it ſelfe the moſt honourable calling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men) to be ſo contemptible and ſo baſely coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of as it is in the World, as the vicious and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:27804:6"/>liues of ſome amongſt vs; for as <hi>Apollonius</hi> is ſaid to haue girded a falſe Prophet of the <hi>Montaniſts,</hi> with his <hi>dic quaeſo, Propheta ludit teſseris ac tabulis, Propheta foeneratur? &amp;c.</hi> So, I would it might not bee ſaid to ſome of ours, and further added to it, <hi>Propheta pugnat, inrat, inebriatur, ſcortatur, fallit, litigat, mundana cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat, ſapit, amat, agit? &amp;c.</hi> Oh that theſe things were not talkt of in <hi>Gath,</hi> and publiſhed in the ſtreets of <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kalon.</hi> Theſe are they that make our calling ſo contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible in the World; for,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>Yee are departed out of the way</hi> (ſaith the Lord to the Prieſts) <hi>yee haue cauſed many to ſtumble at his Law; therefore haue I made you contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and baſe before all the people.</hi> The more ſhame there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is it for ſuch, and the greater ſhall bee their Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who by their diſordered liues, bring this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt vpon our calling, and make the <hi>filth</hi> of their <hi>owne</hi> vicious courſes to be caſt into the <hi>faces of vs all.</hi> Chriſt cals vs the <hi>Salt of the Earth:</hi> and <hi>Salt is good;</hi> Miniſters are vſefull and neceſſary amongſt men;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.13.</note> but <hi>if the Salt haue loſt his ſauour, wherewith ſhall it be ſeaſoned? it is then neither fit for the land nor yet for the dunghill;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 14.34, 35.</note> 
               <hi>but men cast in out.</hi> That is (ſaith Saint <hi>Hierome</hi>) vnſauoury Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are to be depoſed and turned out of the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And ſo is his Expedition ſaid to bee vrged in the Councell of <hi>Baſill</hi> againſt Pope <hi>Eugenius,</hi> for his depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition from the Papacie. And well were it for vs, if ſome vnſauoury ones amongſt vs might bee ſo dealt with; but if they ſcape the hand of Iuſtice at our Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods and Viſitations, I muſt yet ſay to them (as once a Reuerend Father is ſaid to haue ſpoken to the <hi>Councell of Rhemes,</hi> when he ſaw there was no hope of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amongſt them) <hi>fratres aliam vobis pronuntio Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</hi> My Brethren, I muſt put you in minde of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:27804:7"/>Synod, which the great Archbiſhop of our ſoules ſhall hold at his ſecond comming to Iudgement, and then let theſe be ſure that (though now they lurke in <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebris</hi>) they ſhall be found out, and fitted according to their deſerts; for if then they ſhall haue nothing to plead for themſelues, but, <hi>Maſter, haue we not in thy name propheſied?</hi> Chriſt hath told them before hand what they ſhall looke for at that day, <hi>I will ſay to them I know you not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.23.</note> 
               <hi>depart from me yee that worke iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the ſecond thing which they aſcribe to Chriſt; Secondly, <hi>And teacheſt the way of God in truth.</hi> Which, as it was alſo truely ſpoken of Chriſt, though with a bad minde in them that firſt ſpake it, ſo ought it in ſome ſort to bee verified in euery Miniſter of Gods Word.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he that is called to be <hi>a Maſter,</hi> his worke muſt be <hi>to teach;</hi> and ſecondly, the <hi>ſubject</hi> of his Doctrine muſt be the <hi>way of God,</hi> and thirdly, the manner of his teaching it muſt be <hi>in truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Miniſters are not only to know the truth, and to liue according to it themſelues, but to <hi>teach</hi> it to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 1.1.</note> For ſo did Chriſt, <hi>hee fulfilled his Miniſterie in doing and teaching;</hi> Indeed the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith, hee was dumbe as a ſheepe before the Shearer. But wee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reade of him that hee was dumbe as a Shepherd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his ſheepe; but it was his cuſtome at leaſt <hi>euery Sabboth day to preach the Word in the Synagogues.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.16.</note> And himſelfe ſaith, that one chiefe end why he came into the World was to <hi>preach to the poore.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 17.</note> And it was the firſt part of the Apoſtles Commiſſion which they had from him;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19</note> 
               <hi>goe and teach.</hi> We know how fearefully the Lord inueigheth againſt <hi>ſtumbring and ſleepy Watchmen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 56.10</note> whom he cals <hi>dumbe Dagges that barke not;</hi> and wee
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27804:7"/>reade that the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> came downe vpon the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> in the likeneſſe of <hi>fiery tongues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>quia quos miſeris Deus &amp; ardentes pariter &amp; loquentes facit,</hi> whom God ſends, he makes them not only to <hi>burne</hi> in themſelues by the zeale of good Workes, but to <hi>ſhine</hi> to others too by light of Doctrine.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 38.25</note> The Law threatneth <hi>death to the Priest, if hee make not a ſound with his Bels when he goeth into the Sanctuary.</hi> Which, by the Iudgement of all Interpreters, ſignifieth <hi>deadly danger to a dumbe Minister. Morte dignus eſt Sacerdos, à quo vox praedicatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis non auditur</hi> (ſaith one) That Prieſt is not worthy to liue, that doth not vſe to preach the Word of God. And it is a diſmall conditionall <hi>woe,</hi> which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth expreſſely thunder out againſt himſelfe, and, in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, againſt all others; <hi>Vae mihi ſi non euangelizauere:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16.</note> 
               <hi>Woe be to me, if I preach not the Goſpell.</hi> And therefore here you ſee that the intollerable negligence of ſome amongſt vs comes iuſtly to be reprooued; who, it may be, are outwardly <hi>blameleſſe in their lines,</hi> but yet, <hi>ſilent in their Miniſtery:</hi> liuing in the Church like <hi>Lamps with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out light,</hi> or <hi>Bells without clappers,</hi> or as a <hi>Cryer</hi> in a Court <hi>without a voyce;</hi> for, <hi>innocens, abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſermone, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſatio</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Hierome</hi>) <hi>quantum exemplo prodeſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hier. ad Occanum.</note> 
               <hi>tantum ſilentio nocet:</hi> A dumbe Miniſter, though of an innocent life, doth hurt as much by his ſilence, as hee helpes by his example. A Miniſter, by his place, is not only a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> but a <hi>Ruler</hi> amongſt Gods people; not only a <hi>Souldier</hi> of Chriſts, but a <hi>Watchman</hi> of the Lord of Hoaſts; not only a <hi>ſheepe</hi> of the fold, but a <hi>Shepheard</hi> of the flocke; not only a <hi>ſtone</hi> of the building, but a <hi>Builder</hi> of the Houſe of God: not only a <hi>plant</hi> of the Garden, but a <hi>Planter</hi> of the trees thereof: not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>Child</hi> of the Family, but a ſpirituall <hi>Father</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27804:8"/>Children vnto God in Chriſt, and in a word, not only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19</note> a Diſciple of Chriſt himſelfe, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; a Maſter appointed to teach others. And thefore let vs take heed of being <hi>dumbe</hi> in the Miniſtery, leaſt when God ſhall come to vs with, how cameſt <hi>thou</hi> in hither? wee bee ſtrucke <hi>dumbe</hi> by his Maieſtie in the day of his Viſitation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as a Maſters worke is <hi>to teach,</hi> ſo the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect</hi> of his labour, the <hi>matter</hi> that hee is to worke vpon, is, <hi>the way of God,</hi> that is, as <hi>Dauid</hi> expounds it, <hi>The way of Gods Teſtimonies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.34.27, 32.</note> 
               <hi>the way of Gods Precepts, the way of Gods Commandements:</hi> and in plaine tearmes, that manner of liuing here, which God hath preſcribed to vs in his word. Which, in regard of the eminencie, and profitablenes of it, aboue all other wayes that mans wit can finde out, or any other creature make knowne to him; is in other places called the <hi>way of Wiſedome, Knowledge, Truth, Peace, Life, Saluation, &amp;c.</hi> it is here called the <hi>way of God,</hi> ſpecially in three reſpects; becauſe it is <hi>reuealed</hi> of God, <hi>approued</hi> of God, and <hi>leadeth</hi> thoſe that walke in it, to the fruition of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gods Word</hi> then, muſt be the <hi>matter</hi> of our teaching, we may not deliuer any thing elſe, of our owne heads in the roome of it, for Gods way and mans way, the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Gods Word, and the thoughts of mans heart, are as contrary one to the other as light and darkneſſe. <hi>My thoughts are not your thoughts, neither are your wayes my wayes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 55.8, 9</note> 
               <hi>ſaith the Lord; for as the Heauens are higher then the Earth, euen ſo are my wayes higher then your wayes, and my thoughts then you thoughts.</hi> And the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.19.</note> that <hi>the wiſdome of this World is fooliſhneſſe with God.</hi> And therefore we are to looke to it, that wee doe not only <hi>teach,</hi> but that the <hi>matter</hi> of our teaching
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:27804:8"/>bee the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and not the froth of our owne braines, nor the Learning which wee gather out of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Authors, any further then wee finde it conſonant to the Word of God. For Gods way muſt needs be an vndefiled way, but mans way cannot chooſe but bee corrupted; ſeeing that ſuch as the Fountaine is, ſuch muſt needs be the water that runnes from it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thirdly, as the <hi>matter</hi> of our <hi>Ministery</hi> is the <hi>way of God,</hi> ſo the <hi>manner</hi> of our <hi>deliuery</hi> of it muſt bee <hi>in truth. Studie to ſhew thy ſelfe approued of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15</note> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi>) <hi>A Workman that needeth not to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, rightly diuiding the Word of Truth.</hi> So that it is not enough for a Miniſter to teach <hi>the truth,</hi> vnleſſe that he teach it <hi>in truth</hi> too; rightly, and ſo as it ought to be be taught: for a good matter may be marde in the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of it.</p>
            <p>Now, that it may ſo be taught, we muſt teach it, <hi>only, wholy, plainly,</hi> and <hi>wiſely.</hi> Only without addition, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without diminution, plainly without affectation, and wiſely without indiſcretion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the way of Truth may be taught in truth; it is <hi>only</hi> to be taught. As we muſt teach nothing elſe for it, ſo wee may mixe nothing elſe with it. It is a perfect way of it ſelfe, <hi>which is able to make vs wiſe vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</hi> And <hi>to make the man of God perfect,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3 15</note> 
               <hi>thorowly furniſhed vnto all good works.</hi> And therefore to adde to it (whether our owne inuentions, or other mens traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if they be contrary, or though they be but diuers from it, if they bee added to it, as of the ſame neceſſitie and authority, I ſay ſo to adde to it) is to alter and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the perfection of it, making it to bee no longer Gods way but mans way. For Gods way is like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, it will brooke no mixture, it will either be alwaies
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27804:9"/>ſimple and of it ſelfe, or elſe not at all the way of God, as the <hi>Arke</hi> and <hi>Dagon</hi> would not ſtand together in one houſe,<note place="margin">1. 5 <hi>am.</hi> 5 3.</note> ſo Gods way and mans wit will not be moulded vp together into a body of one Religion, a ladder of ſuch compound ſtuffe will certainly neuer hold toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for a man to get to heauen by it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And ſecondly, as it muſt bee taught <hi>onely</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>addition,</hi> ſo <hi>wholly too,</hi> without <hi>diminution;</hi> for ſo runnes the Apoſtolicall commiſſion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.10</note> goe and teach <hi>all things, whatſoeuer I haue commanded you.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth as much of himſelfe to the Elders of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 20.20.</note> 
               <hi>I haue kept back nothing from you,</hi> ſaith he, and afterward he expounds himſelfe more fully, when he ſaith,<note place="margin">26.</note> 
               <hi>I take you to record this day, that I am free from the bloud of all men, for I haue not ſhunned to declare vnto you all the counſell of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">27.</note> So that as there is no defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie in Gods Word to be ſupplyed by mans inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo there is no ſuperfluitie in it neither, to be pared away, or concealed from the world at mans diſcretion. There can bee no danger in preaching all that to our people (ſo it be done in ſeaſon, and with that diſcretion which is requiſite in a Miniſter of the Goſpell) which God hath not made daintie to reueale to vs in his Word.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, that it may bee taught in truth, it muſt bee taught <hi>plainly</hi> without <hi>affectation: all things must be done in the Church vnto edification:</hi> and, <hi>be that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in an vnknowne tongue, edifieth himſelfe</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>but he that prophecieth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.4.</note> 
               <hi>edifieth the Church.</hi> And therefore afterward, he profeſſeth of himſelfe, <hi>that in the Church he had rather ſpeake fiue wordes ſo with his owne vnderſtanding, that by his voyce he might teach others alſo, then ten thouſand wordes in an vnknowne
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:27804:9"/>tongue.</hi> Now what difference is there betwixt ſpeaking to the common people in an vnknowne tongue, and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſuch an affected ſublimitie of phraſe, and ſuch a Romiſh Engliſh (as one fitly calls it) that plaine En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhmen can no more vnderſtand what is ſpoken, then if he that preacheth, were a Barbarian to them, and they to him: A fault, which ſome that <hi>Maſter it</hi> amongſt vs, are but too guiltie of, to the great hurt of their ſimple Auditories, and the too palpable diſcouerie of their owne inſinceritie; for what is this, but to act the parts of the vnfaithfull Ieſuites, and Prieſts of Rome and Rhemes? who doe purpoſely ſo wrap vp the light of Gods Word in a darke clowd of abſolete and barbarous wordes, that all wiſe men ſee, they labour rather to procure admiration to themſelues, then glorie to God, and ſaluation to his Church. It was a iudgement vpon the Iewes, that <hi>Christ preacht to them in parables,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.11</note> that ſo <hi>they might heare, and yet not vnderſtand;</hi> and what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is there betwixt a parable and an affected kinde of eloquence, which tranſcends the capacitie of our Hearers?<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17.</note> when Chriſt ſent <hi>Paul</hi> to preach the Goſpell to the Gentiles, he ſaith, he was <hi>commanded to preach it not with wiſedome of wordes:</hi> and in obedience to this commandement, he tells the Corinthians in the next Chapter,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.1, 4.</note> that <hi>he came not to them in excellency of ſpeech and of wiſedome, nor was his preaching with entiſing wordes of mans wiſedome, but in demonſtration of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and of power.</hi> In the feare of God then, let not vs be aſhamed to follow the example of ſo great an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, that it may appeare to the world that we ſeeke not our ſelues, but the glorie of God in Chriſt, and the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of our Hearers; and that in the teſtimonie of a good conſcience, we may ſay with the ſame Apoſtle,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:27804:10"/>
               <hi>we haue renounced the hidden things of diſhoneſtie,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2.</note> not wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in craftineſſe, nor handling the Word of God deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, but by manifeſtation of the truth, commending our ſelues to euery mans conſcience in the ſight of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, it muſt be taught <hi>wiſely</hi> without <hi>indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion;</hi> a faithfull and wiſe ſeruant fit to be made Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ouer Gods houſhold,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.42.</note> doth not onely giue his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſeruants meate, and in due ſeaſon, but he giues to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one their portion. The ſame diſh of meate is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fit for euery ones perſon, nor agreeable to euery ones ſtomack. There is great difference of Hearers in euery Auditorie: ſome are <hi>ignorant,</hi> and they muſt be <hi>inſtructed,</hi> ſome are <hi>erronious,</hi> and they muſt be <hi>confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;</hi> ſome are <hi>diſordered,</hi> and they muſt be <hi>admoniſhed;</hi> ſome are <hi>weake,</hi> and they muſt be <hi>ſtrengthened;</hi> ſome are <hi>diſtreſſed,</hi> and they muſt be <hi>comforted;</hi> ſome are <hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctible,</hi> and they muſt be <hi>allured;</hi> and ſome are <hi>obſtinate,</hi> and they muſt be <hi>terrified;</hi> ſo that there is great pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence required in fitting the matter of our diſcourſe, to their ſeuerall eſtates and neceſſities: And to this end, as our Auditories are mixt, ſo ſhould our teaching be, we are to ſing at once, both of <hi>Mercy</hi> and of <hi>Iudgement;</hi> to bring <hi>new</hi> and <hi>old</hi> together out of our treaſurie; to powre <hi>Wine</hi> and <hi>Oile</hi> together into the wounds of our Patients, and not to vſe one ſalue onely for euery ſore, nor to harpe alwayes to them vpon one ſtring.</p>
            <p>And as our matter muſt be good ſpirituall food in it ſelfe, and various; fitted to their ſeuerall conditions: ſo muſt it be cleanly dreſſed and diſht vp, and skilfully handled in the preparing of it for them and preſenting of it to them.<note place="margin">Omne tulit punctum, &amp;c.</note> He beareth away the <hi>golden bell</hi> indeed, that deliuereth a <hi>profitable</hi> ſpeech in a <hi>pleaſant</hi> ſtile: whereas <hi>good matter</hi> ſlubbered vp <hi>in rude termes,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:27804:10"/>both <hi>loathſome</hi> to the hearers, and <hi>diſgracefull to</hi> the teachers of it. Salomon ſaith in the perſon of Chriſt that <hi>the lips of his Spouſe</hi> (and they are the preachers of his Church) <hi>drop as the Hony Combe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>Hony and Milke are vnder her tongue.</hi> Now Hony and Milke we know, are both <hi>ſweet</hi> and <hi>wholeſome,</hi> pleaſant in taſte, and good for nouriſhment: ſo ſhould a Preachers ſpeech bee; clothed with comely words, which are as well delightfull to the Eare, as profitable to the Hearer.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Preacher</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> in an other place <hi>did not only teach the people knowledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>and write words of truth, and that which was vpright, but he ſought to find out accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, or delightfull words to deliuer his matter in;</hi> and ſo ſhould we; for our nature is ſoone wearie, euen of good things, vnleſſe wee take pleaſure in them. And therfore <hi>mulcendi ſunt auditores, ſermonis dulcedine ne vtilia inu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiliter audiant:</hi> wee are to ſeeke out delightfull words for our hearers, leaſt they heare the profitable matter which we ſpeak of to them, without any profit to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Diuinitie is a graue Matron, who, as ſhe abhors <hi>gariſhneſſe,</hi> ſo ſhe loues <hi>comelineſſe.</hi> And therefore they doe both alike offer her great indignitie, who either pranke her vp in the <hi>light</hi> and <hi>vaine-faſhion</hi> of <hi>wanton words,</hi> or <hi>careleſly</hi> preſent her in a <hi>looſe</hi> and <hi>ragged ſpeech</hi> to the eares of their Auditors. And therefore, that we may rightly diuide the word of truth, it concernes vs to be carefull that wee ſhew our ſelues as well <hi>skilfull</hi> as <hi>faithfull,</hi> in the teaching of it; leaſt our negligent hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of it, make it to be <hi>neglected of,</hi> and <hi>vnprofitable</hi> to our hearers.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing which they aſcribe to Chriſt is, that he was no reſpecter of mans perſon; in theſe words, <hi>neither careſt thou for any man, for thou regardeſt not the perſon of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:27804:11"/>men.</hi> Which alſo, as it was true in Chriſt; ſo ought it to bee in euery maſter. For <hi>they which will goe about to pleaſe men</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>are not the ſeruants of Chriſt</hi> when truth is to be taught,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.10.</note> falſhood to be confuted, vice to be diſcouered and condemned, and vertue to be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced, and encouraged, and that in the name, and by the word of God, what an high ſinne were it for vs then, to deale partially with men, for loue or feare of their outward perſons? we may not do it, and that we do it not, let vs call to mind how <hi>Eliah</hi> behaued himſelfe againſt <hi>Ahab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 18.18.</note> in condemning his Idolatrous courſes, and <hi>Eliſhah</hi> againſt <hi>Iehoram,</hi> King of Iſrael, when he was in the companie of <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> the King of <hi>Iudah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Kings</hi> 3.13.</note> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> againſt <hi>Dauid</hi> in telling him of his Adulterie with <hi>Vriahs</hi> wife,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.7 <hi>Luke</hi> 3.19.</note> and <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> againſt <hi>Herod</hi> in reprouing him for <hi>Herodias</hi> his brother <hi>Philips</hi> wife; and for all the euill which <hi>Herod</hi> had done, though theſe were Kings. And to theſe might be added the examples of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and Apoſtolicke men in the times of the Primitiue Church, who neither for loue, nor hope, nor feare, nor any other reſpect, would euer bee drawne to deale par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially in their teaching the way of God to the world. Let vs therefore follow their examples, aſſuring our ſelues, that what God ſpake to the Prophet <hi>Ieremie,</hi> is in him ſpoken to euery one of vs. <hi>Gird vp thy loynes, and ariſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>and ſpeake vnto them, all that I commaund thee, be not diſmayed at their faces, least I confound thee before them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, from theſe things, thus opened and appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to our <hi>Maſters</hi> in Gods houſe, I might gather many leſſons too, for our <hi>ſchollers</hi> to take out. But becauſe the time hath preuented me, I will but point at two or three of them in a word and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, ſeeing our office is as <hi>Maſters</hi> in Gods houſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:27804:11"/>to <hi>teach</hi> his people; here you <hi>learners</hi> may ſee how you are to eſteeme, and what vſe you are to make both of our <hi>office</hi> and <hi>perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, our office is to <hi>teach,</hi> which infers, that your dutie is to <hi>learne;</hi> therefore it is not enough for you with patience to giue vs the <hi>hearing,</hi> but you ought carefully to <hi>heed, remember,</hi> and <hi>carrie</hi> away what you heare; for that is the end why maſters teach their ſchollers, not that they may tickle their eares with a tale for a while, and ſo farewell, but that they may be bettered in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for our <hi>Perſons,</hi> this title of <hi>Teachers,</hi> teacheth you how to eſteeme and vſe vs;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17.</note> let the <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders which rule well</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>be counted worthy double honour, eſpecially they which labour in the Word and Doctrine,</hi> which double honour hath beene euer vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troleably acknowledged, the honour of <hi>reuerence</hi> and <hi>maintenance,</hi> ſuch as befits our calling; both which, thoſe which are taught by vs, are bound by the Lawes of God and Nations, freely and fully to affoord to vs.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the honour of <hi>reuerence,</hi> it is the Apoſtles owne exhortation to hearers;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>wee beſeech you Brethren to know them which labour among you, and are ouer you in the Lord, that you eſteeme very highly of them in loue far their worke ſake.</hi> And indeed not to reuerence Miniſters for their work ſake, is to deſpiſe God himſelfe, whoſe work they doe, and whoſe <hi>Embaſſadors</hi> they are vnto you; for ſo ſaith Chriſt, <hi>he that deſpiſeth you deſpiſeth mee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 10.16</note> 
               <hi>and he that deſpiſeth me, deſpiſeth him that ſent mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, for the honour of <hi>maintenance,</hi> it is the Apoſtles owne rule too;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>let him that is taught in the Word, make him that hath taught him, partaker of all his goods; or,</hi> (as our laſt tranſlation renders it) <hi>communicate
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:27804:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>vnto him in all good things;</hi> meaning in the vſe of all ſuch outward and wordly bleſſings as God hath beſtowed vpon the <hi>learner. Nor is this any great matter,</hi> (ſaith he in an other place,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.11 13, 14.</note> though carnall men may thinke it ſo;) <hi>that we ſhould reap your carnall things, ſeeing we haue ſowen vnto you ſpirituall things;</hi> nay it is <hi>Gods own ordinance that us they which waited at the Altar, liued of the Altar; ſo they which preach the Goſpel, ſhould liue of the Goſpel.</hi> And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, by force or fraud to detaine that from vs, which the Lawes of God doe giue, and of men, doe confirme vnto vs for our maintenance, is to diſhonour vs, and in vs, to diſhonour God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Malac.</hi> 3.9.</note> and to pull downe his curſe vpon your ſelues and vpon all that you poſſeſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſeeing that which we are to teach is <hi>the way of God,</hi> this teacheth you, that you are to <hi>walke in it</hi> for thats the end why men ſeeke to know <hi>wayes,</hi> that they may <hi>trauell</hi> in them to the places which they deſire to come to; if you had not need to know this way, what ſhould we doe teaching of it to you? and what vſe elſe, can a way be put to by you, but to be trauelled in? there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when you haue learned it from vs, walke in it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly; or elſe our teaching, and your learning of it, will bring you neuer a whit the nearer to heauen.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as we are to teach it <hi>in truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſo are you to walke in it; that is, to beleeue and practiſe it <hi>only</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>adding</hi> your owne deuiſes to it, and <hi>wholy,</hi> without preſuming to <hi>paſſe ouer</hi> any part of it vnpractiſed, as occaſion to doe it is offered vnto you; for if any man ſhall adde vnto it, God ſhall adde vnto him the plagues that are written in his Booke; and if any ſhall take away from it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 22.18.</note> God ſhall take away his part out of the Booke of life.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, as wee are to teach Gods way <hi>without reſpect
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:27804:12"/>of men or perſons,</hi> ſo are you to practiſe it too: you may not conceale, nor corrupt the truth in your words, nor doe any thing contrary to equity, or Chriſtian Charity in your deeds, neither for fauour of friends, nor feare of great men, nor hope of profit, nor hatred of enemies, nor contempt of Inferiours, nor any other reſpect what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer; for this is to ſet vp the <hi>Creature</hi> aboue the <hi>Creator.</hi> God only is to bee loued, and feared ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply for himſelfe; and aboue all things elſe that are; and all things elſe, reſpectiuely to him; as hee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects vs in his Word. So that if any of you fauour an vniuſt cauſe, for his ſake whoſe cauſe it is, in ſo doing you commit Idolatry, making him whoſe vniuſt cauſe you ſo fauour, your God; in as much as you preferre him and his falſhood, before God and his Truth; and therefore take heed, that through reſpect of mens per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons you renounce not your Religion, and turne Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels. <hi>Amicus ſit</hi> Plato, <hi>magis amica veritas:</hi> It is good for a man, though to loue his friend well, yet ſtill to preferre the Truth before him.</p>
            <p>And by our thus <hi>teaching</hi> and <hi>liuing,</hi> and your thus <hi>learning</hi> and <hi>walking,</hi> both wee and you ſhall be ſure at the laſt, to obtaine the end of our faith and paines which ſhall be the ſaluation of our ſoules. Which God the Father grant to vs, through the merits of his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus, and prepare vs to, by the power of his ho-Spirit; to which Trinitie in Vnitie, the only true, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal and inuiſible God, be aſcribed all Praiſe, Wiſdome, Maieſtie, Might, and Dominion, now, and for euermore.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
